Guide to the Anna and Stanley Wilson Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Anna and Stanley Wilson Papers
1892-1951
1918-1923
RG 220
Yale University Divinity School Library
2.5
(4 boxes)
This collection documents the life and work of Anna Lane Wilson and Stanley Wilson, who were missionaries in China from 1917 to 1949, primarily serving at Yenching University. Of particular note are Anna Wilson's letters to family in the United States and journals document her voyage to China, missionary life, Chinese customs and celebrations, dress, architecture, the flu epidemic, climate, and political events.
Wilson, Anna Lane, 1892-1981
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Helen Wilson Saunders, 2009
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Anna Marie Lane Wilson (1892-1981) served as a missionary to China under the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions from 1919 to 1949. Leaving for China in September 1918, she taught Biology, Chemistry and other subjects at the North China Union Woman's College for five years and then, in 1923, married Stanley Davis Wilson.
Stanley Wilson(1881-1970) was professor of Chemistry at the Peking Union Medical College (supported by the Rockefeller Foundation). Shortly later, the Wilsons moved to the newly formed Yenching University outside Peking, where they lived and worked until interrupted by World War II in 1941. They were on furlough in the United States in 1924-1925. Stanley Wilson did not go to China as a missionary, but after he married Anna Lane and began his work at Yenching University, he was supported by the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions. In accordance with the custom at the time, Anna Lane no longer taught at the University following her marriage. Stanley Wilson was interned by the Japanese and repatriated half way through the war in a prisoner exchange. After the war the Wilsons returned to Yenching where they worked for another three years and were there during the takeover by the Communist regime, finally returning to California and retirement in 1949.
Scope and Contents
Series I - V of this collection primarily document the life and work of Anna Lane Wilson in China from 1918-1923. Detailed letters to family in the United States document her voyage to China, missionary life, Chinese customs and celebrations, dress, architecture, the flu epidemic, climate and relations/conflicts between Japan and China. Most of the letters are from before Anna's marriage to Stanley Wilson in 1923 and the subsequent births of their daughters Helen and Marian. Many of the letters in the collection have been transcribed by Anna Lane Wilson's daughter Helen Wilson Saunders. The transcriptions are available in printed form, filed with the originals, and also on a CD.
In addition to family correspondence, there is a small amount of general correspondence primarily to/from Stanley Wilson. Journals of Anna Lane Wilson from 1918-1919 and 1923 describe her voyage to China, her first year of work and a return trip to the United States. Collected material primarily relates to Peking University, later known as Yenching University.
Photographs in Series V include documentation of North China Union Woman's College, Yenching University, Peking Union Medical College and the Beijing area.
Series VI, Addendum, represents papers of Anna and Stanley Wilson that had been donated to the Library at an earlier times and were previously included in Record Group 8, China Records Project Miscellaneous Personal Papers. The correspondence in Series VI is primarily from a later period and documents Stanley Wilson's period of separation from his family during the Sino-Japanese war, including his internment by the Japanese. Also included are scientific writings of Wilson and documentation relating to Yenching University at the time of the Communist takeover in 1948-1949.
Additional documentation related to the work of Stanley and Anna Wilson at Yenching University is located in YDSL Record Group No. 11, Archives of the United Board for Christian Higher Education in Asia.
Arrangement
I. Family Correspondence, 1918-1935
II. General Correspondence, 1920-1923
III. Journals, 1918-1923
IV. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1892-1948
V. Photographs, 1919-1951
VI. Addendum, 1917-1950
Missions -- China; Missionaries; Wilson, Anna Lane, 1892-1981; Wilson, Stanley Davis, 1881-1970; Yanjing da xue
- Family correspondence, 1918-1935; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  These letters are from Anna Lane Wilson to her family in the U.S. A CD containing electronic copies of transcriptions of many of them is in the first folder.
  - Incl. re. Preparations for voyage from Vancouver to China, 1918 Aug-Sep 5 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Incl. re. Seasickness; crossing international date line; war in Egypt, 1918 Sep 11-21 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Incl. at Kobe, Japan, 1918 Sep 21-27 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Incl. re. arrival at North China Women's College in Peking, Learning Chinese; Red Cross knitting for Siberia; cultural differences (beauty, dress, binding of feet); conditions in Russia and Balkans; Spanish influenza; Temple of Heaven; Summer Palace; celebration of founding of Republic., 1918 Oct-Dec (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Incl. re. Chinese troops celebrating victory in Forbidden City; expectations of Chinese girls 12-16 yrs., 1918 Dec 11 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Incl. re. Christmas celebrations; rumors from Vladivostok Czechs killed; menus for meals; boys doing housekeeping; church entertainments., 1918 Dec 25 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Incl. re. Flu epidemic; Chinese money; funeral and wedding customs; calligraphy; 70,000 people in Peking destitute - beggars; China shortage of wood, 1919 Jan (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Incl. re. Chinese New Year; entertaining; New Year customs; city and shops; concerns about Peace Conference – relations between China/Japan; foot binding custom, 1919 Feb (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Incl. re. Chinese foreign relations – North/South; Japanese threat; life of English/American; servants; Korea (freedom from Japanese rule); visit to tombs of Manchu Emperors, 1919 Mar (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Incl. re. Chinese schools - government higher normal school – men; Rockefeller Premedical School; life in Peking, 1919 Apr (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Incl. re. Visit to Tsing Hua School (Indemnity College); camphor wood box; Japan takes Shantung; student march to Ts'ao Yulin home ("traitor"); role of League of Nations ("agent that insures Japan the fruits of her villainy"); Dr. Dickinson study of medical situation in China, 1919 May (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Incl. re. Korea travel ill advised; sand fly infestation; student movement; college for women; women protest; possibility of revelution – student strikes, marches, arrests; boycott on Japanese goods; building in brick – not wood; German evacuation back to Germany, 1919 Jun (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - From Peitaiho summer resort, incl. re. School tuition; Women's Medical School; Rockefeller School; salaries (missionaries vs medical school doctors); chancellor dismissed; North/South civil war, 1919 Jul (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - From Petaiho summer resort, incl. re. American Board Missions meeting; educational meetings; Interchurch Movement; trip to Great Wall, 1919 Aug (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Incl.re. Opening of school; teaching 45 hrs/wk English in Tungchou, 1919 Sep-Oct 4 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Incl. re. Chinese wedding; recall of 1912 revolution event where Manchu women and children escaped into mission for safety, 1919 Oct 20-Nov (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Incl. re. suffering from flu, going to hospital; John Dewey of Columbia visits Peking; Christmas celebration; consideration of moving school to Shantung province near medical school for men, 1919 Dec (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Incl. re. Dr. Arthur Smith visit; Catholic/Protestant relations; living on salary; connections in Peking; Methodist East Asia Conference; China Medical Conference; Provisional Education Assoc.; student "agitations"; Japan takes over Germany's right in Shantung; policy for medical schools discussion., 1920 Jan-Feb (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Incl. re. celebration of school's affiliation with University; missionaries contact with community and knowledge of native conditions; Girl's schools – differences in motivation for attending; flu – how it is treated in China; 2 New Years; celebrations and customs; Gov't Univ. in Peking open to women, 1920 Mar (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Incl. re. celebration of Passion Week; Biology class using lab. at Rockefeller Pre Med. School; coal mine; Buddhist temple' Tungchou – business session, appointing Chinese to places of responsibility; requesting salary raise; scarlet fever; 1st man to fly Rome to Tokyo, 1920 Apr-May (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Incl. re. Yutaoho, Fenchoufu valley/canyon description; July 4th celebration; typhus; village life; Pye's missionary family life/Watson medical family life; visitors from Japan Sunday School Convention, 1920 Jun-Oct (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Incl. re. Car trip Techow to Linching; circus; student conference at Indemnity College;; Dr. Boynton (and Grace) arrive; meeting of Wen Yu Hui – dinner and lecture on Russion Bolshevism, 1921 Apr-1922 Mar (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Incl.from Wa Fo Ssu (temple in Western Hills), and re. water shortage; flooding, mosquitos, flies, dysentery; trains unavailable due to Military; Ginling Univ.; Miss Ting – YMCA Nat'l Sec. (1st for Chinese); student body in transition; tour down Yangtze; Gen. Feng and exploits, 1922 Jun-Jul (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Incl. re. Mrs. Packard's tea for Anna; Peking Univ. Medical School attendees; Fung Fu dinner; wedding plans; a daily schedule; shopping, 1922 Nov (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Incl. re. Auto trip to hills; shopping for Chinese art, 1922 Dec (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Incl.re. Chinese New Year; sick with "grippe"; discussion of morals, 1923 Feb (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Incl. re. Wedding plans; return to U.S. via Rangoon; Calcutta; furlough in NY, 1923 May - 1924 Jan (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Incl. re. Visit to Omaha; return to China; Feng Yu Hsiang seizes Chinese president and Emperor's stronghold – they flee; R.R. lines from Shanghai to Peking cut; visit of mother; work as "Sales Department" of Faculty Cross Stitch work, 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Incl. re. Political unrest and domestic life, 1928-1932 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Incl. re. Sale of handmade linens; difficulty in maintaining mission and university; John R. Mott speech at hotel; Paul Monroe attending China Board Medical meeting; Teilhard de Chardin speech at Peking Society Of Natural History, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- General Correspondence, 1920-1944; Series II
  - Circular letter from Anna Lane to "First Central Church" in the U.S., 1920 Jan (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Letters to Stanley Wilson re. engagement to Anna Lane, incl. from Mildred Pyke, Grace Boynton, Way Sung New, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Letters to Anna Lane from Luella Miner, 1923, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Letter to "Dear Friends" from Stanley Wilson describing his experiences in the Weihsien internment camp, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Journals of Anna Lane Wilson, 1918-1923; Series III
  - Journal describing voyage to China and first year of work, 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Journal describing voyage from Peking to Omaha, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1892-1948; Series IV
  - Service commissioning Anna Lane; Program from affiliation ceremony of North China Women's College to Peking University; Peking University commencement announcement, 1918-1920 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Notice to foreigners about proceeding to Legation Quarters if in danger, newspaper clipping re. Lloyd George speech, Chinese language material, 1924, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Yenching University identification cards for Helen Wilson and Anna Lane Wilson; Typed transcripts of biographical notes written by Anna Lane Wilson and Stanley D. Wilson; excerpts about Anna from journal written by her mother, 1892-1948, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Photographs, 1919-1951; Series V
  - Yenching University: site for new campus, field day, ca. 1920, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Yenching University: Chemistry Department, labs, 1936-1947, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Yenching University: students, 1938-1948, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Yenching University: faculty and staff, including Anna andStanley Wilson, Leighton Stuart. Langdon Gilkey, 1926-1949 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Yenching University: campus and buildings (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Yenching University: unidentified individuals, 1949-1951 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Kuan Tso Ling (in mountains west of BaoTing Fu, 1935-1937 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - North China Union Woman's College Tung Fu campus: Students, ca. 1919-1920. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - North China Union Woman's College Tung Fu campus: buildings and people - including Anna Lane, Alice Frame, Luella Miner, ca. 1919-1920 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - North China Union Woman's College Tung Fu campus: Shakespeare play put on by students, ca. 1919-1920 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - North China Union Woman's College Tung Fu campus: Chinese wedding demonstration put on by students, faculty and staff, ca. 1919-1920 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - North China Union Woman's College Tung Fu campus: students and campus, ca. 1919-1920 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Peitaiho summer resort, ca. 1919 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Peking: Armistice Day, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Peking: children, workers, scenes, ca. 1919-1923 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Peking: boats, water, funeral, buildings, ca. 1919-1923 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Peking: buildings, ca. 1919-1923 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Trip to Fenchow, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Peking Union Medical College (set of colored postcards), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Peking scenes, including Forbidden City, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Peking scenes, including Summer and Winter Palaces (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Album: "Photographs of Anna and Stanley Wilson in China 1918-1948" including scenes from trips, Peking Union Medical College (Box OV1)
- Addendum, Series VI
  - Immediate family correspondence
    Correspondence in this subseries is primarily between Anna and Stanley Wilson and their daughters.
    - Stanley to wife and daughters, from Peking, 1941 April-June (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Stanley to wife and daughters, from Peking and Peitaiho, 1941 July-August (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Stanley to wife and daughters, from Peking, 1941 September-November (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Stanley to/from wife and daughters, from Peking, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Students had been evacuated from Yenching University due to Sino-Japanese war. Some letters conveyed via International Red Cross.
    - Stanley to/from wife and daughters, from Peking, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Extended family correspondence
    Correspondence in this subseries is primarily with the extended family of Stanley Wilson.
    - Stanley and Anna to his sister Amy Wilson and to "family", 1917-1919, 1926-1930 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - To sisters, aunt, father, 1932-1937 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - To sisters, aunt, 1938-1940 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - To/from sisters, 1941-1943 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - General correspondence
    - Circular letters from Wilsons, 1931-1941 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Letters from friends and missionary colleagues, 1941-1950 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Letters of others, including circular letters of missionary colleagues, 1933, 1942-1949 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Writings
    - Offprints of scientific articles co-authored by Stanley Wilson, 1930-1937 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Offprints of scientific articles co-authored by Stanley Wilson, 1938-1949 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Writings of others, including "Chemistry in China" by William Adolph, "The Christian Attitude to Communism" by Robert James McCracken, 1945-1948 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Collected material
    - Chinese language materials (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Documentation related to conditions in China, including during occupation of Yenching University by Japanese, 1933, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Documentation regarding student movements at Yenching University and conditions prior to Communist liberation, 1948-1949 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Personal items and memorabilia
    - Biographical documentation, including from Stanley's period of internment in Peking, and repatriation on Gripsholm, 1943, no date (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Programs from events at Yenching University, 1936-1948, no date (Box 3, Folder 20)